<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Performance | J@ArangoDB]]></title>
  <link href="http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/categories/performance/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jsteemann.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-23T11:20:53+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://jsteemann.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jsteemann]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[COLLECTing With a Hash Table]]></title>
    <link href="http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/04/22/collecting-with-a-hash-table/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-22T13:53:10+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/04/22/collecting-with-a-hash-table</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>ArangoDB 2.6 will feature an alternative <strong>hash</strong> implementation of the AQL <code>COLLECT</code>
operation. The new implementation can speed up some AQL queries that can not exploit indexes
on the <code>COLLECT</code> group criteria.</p>

<p>This blog post provides a preview of the feature and shows some nice performance improvements.
It also explains the <code>COLLECT</code>-related optimizer parts and how the optimizer will decide whether
to use the new or the traditional implementation.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Introduction to COLLECT</h2>

<p>A quick recap: in AQL, the <code>COLLECT</code> operation can be used for grouping and optionally counting values.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an example, using flight data:</p>

<p><code>plain AQL COLLECT example
FOR flight IN flights
  COLLECT from = flight._from WITH COUNT INTO count
  RETURN { from: from, count: count }
</code></p>

<p>This query will iterate over all documents in collection <code>flights</code>, and count the
number of flights per different <code>_from</code> value (origin airport). The query result will
contain only unique <code>from</code> values plus a counter for each:</p>

<p><code>json query result, grouped by from
[
  { "from" : "airports/ABE", "count" : 6205 },
  { "from" : "airports/ABQ", "count" : 39346 },
  { "from" : "airports/ACV", "count" : 362 },
  ...
  { "from" : "airports/YAP", "count" : 285 },
  { "from" : "airports/YKM", "count" : 879 },
  { "from" : "airports/YUM", "count" : 2275 }
]
</code></p>

<p>As the <code>COLLECT</code> will group its result according to the specified group criteria (<code>flights._from</code>
in the above query), it needs a way of figuring out to which group any input value does belong.</p>

<p>Before ArangoDB 2.6, there was a single method for determining the group. Starting with ArangoDB
2.6, the query optimizer can choose between two different <code>COLLECT</code> methods, the <strong>sorted</strong> method
and the <strong>hash</strong> method.</p>

<h2>Sorted COLLECT method</h2>

<p>The traditional method for determining the group values is the <strong>sorted</strong> method. It has been
available in ArangoDB since the very start.</p>

<p>The sorted method of <code>COLLECT</code> requires its input to be sorted by the group criteria specified
in the <code>COLLECT</code> statement. Because there is no guarantee that the input data are already sorted
in the same way, the query optimizer will automatically insert a <code>SORT</code> statement into the query
in front of the <code>COLLECT</code>. In case there is a sorted index present on the group criteria attributes,
the optimizer may be able to optimize away the <code>SORT</code> again. If there is no sorted index present
on the group criteria attributes, the <code>SORT</code> will remain in the execution plan.</p>

<p>Here is the execution plan for the above query using the <strong>sorted</strong> method of <code>COLLECT</code>. We can see
the extra <code>SortNode</code> with id #7 being added by the optimizer in front of the <code>COLLECT</code>:</p>

<p><img src="/downloads/screenshots/collect-sorted.png"></p>

<p>The <strong>sorted</strong> method of <code>COLLECT</code> is efficient because it can write out a group result whenever
an input value will start a new group. Therefore it does not need to keep the whole <code>COLLECT</code>
result in memory. The downside of using the sorted method is that it requires its input to be
sorted, and that this requires adding an extra <code>SORT</code> for not properly sorted input.</p>

<h2>Hash COLLECT method</h2>

<p>Since ArangoDB 2.6, the query optimizer can also employ the <strong>hash</strong> method for <code>COLLECT</code>. The
hash method works by assigning the input values of the <code>COLLECT</code> to slots in a hash table. It
does not require its input to be sorted. Because the entries in the hash table do not have a
particular order, the query optimizer will add a post-<code>COLLECT</code> <code>SORT</code> statement. With this extra
sort of the <code>COLLECT</code> result, the optimizer ensures that the output of the sorted <code>COLLECT</code> will
be the same as the output of the hash <code>COLLECT</code>.</p>

<p>Here is the execution plan for the above query when using the <strong>hash</strong> method of <code>COLLECT</code>.
Here we can see the extra <code>SortNode</code> with id #7 being added post-<code>COLLECT</code>:</p>

<p><img src="/downloads/screenshots/collect-hash.png"></p>

<p>The <strong>hash</strong> method is beneficial because it does not require sorted input and thus no extra
<code>SORT</code> step in front. However, as the input is not sorted, it is never clear when a group is
actually finished. The hash method therefore needs to build the whole <code>COLLECT</code> result in memory
until the input is exhausted. Then it can safely write out all group results. Additionally,
the result of the hash <code>COLLECT</code> is unsorted. Therefore the optimizer will add a post-<code>COLLECT</code>
sort to ensure the result will be identical to a <strong>sorted</strong> <code>COLLECT</code>.</p>

<h2>Which method will be used when?</h2>

<p>The query optimizer will always take the initial query plan and specialize its <code>COLLECT</code> nodes to
using the <strong>sorted</strong> method. It will also add the pre-<code>COLLECT</code> <code>SORT</code> in the original plan.</p>

<p>In addition, for every <code>COLLECT</code> statement not using an <code>INTO</code> clause, the optimizer will create
a plan variant that uses the <strong>hash</strong> method. In that plan variant, the post-<code>COLLECT</code> <code>SORT</code>
will be added. Note that a <code>WITH COUNT INTO</code> is still ok here, but that using a regular <code>INTO</code>
clause will disable the usage of the <strong>hash</strong> method:</p>

<p><code>plain a query that cannot use the hash method
FOR flight IN flights
  COLLECT from = flight._from INTO allFlights
  RETURN { from: from, flights: allFlights }
</code></p>

<p>If more than one <code>COLLECT</code> method can be used for a query, the created plans will be shipped through
the regular optimization pipeline. In the end, the optimizer will pick the plan with the lowest
estimated total cost as it will do for all other queries.</p>

<p>The <strong>hash</strong> variant does not require an up-front sort of the <code>COLLECT</code> input, and will thus be
preferred over the <strong>sorted</strong> method if the optimizer estimates many input elements for the <code>COLLECT</code>
and cannot use an index to process them in already sorted order. In this case, the optimizer
will estimate that post-sorting the result of the <strong>hash</strong> <code>COLLECT</code> will be more efficient than
pre-sorting the input for the <strong>sorted</strong> <code>COLLECT</code>.</p>

<p>The main assumption behind this estimation is that the result of any <code>COLLECT</code> statement will
contain at most as many elements as there are input elements to it. Therefore, the output of
a <code>COLLECT</code> is likely to be smaller (in terms of rows) than its input, making post-sorting more
efficient than pre-sorting.</p>

<p>If there is a sorted index on the <code>COLLECT</code> group criteria that the optimizer can exploit, the
optimizer will pick the <strong>sorted</strong> method because thanks to the index it can optimize away the
pre-<code>COLLECT</code> sort, leaving no sorts left in the final execution plan.</p>

<p>To override the optimizer decision, <code>COLLECT</code> statements now have an <code>OPTIONS</code> modifier. This
modifier can be used to force the optimizer to use the <strong>sorted</strong> variant:</p>

<p><code>plain forcing the use of the sorted variant
FOR flight IN flights
  COLLECT from = flight._from WITH COUNT INTO count OPTIONS { method: "sorted" }
  RETURN { from: from, count: count }
</code></p>

<p>Note that specifying <strong>hash</strong> in <code>method</code> will not force the optimizer to use the <strong>hash</strong> method.
The reason is that the <strong>hash</strong> variant cannot be used for all queries (only <code>COLLECT</code> statements
without an <code>INTO</code> clause are eligible). If <code>OPTIONS</code> are omitted or any other method than <code>sorted</code>
is specified, the optimizer will ignore it and use its regular cost estimations.</p>

<h2>Understanding execution plans</h2>

<p>Which method is actually used in a query can found out by explaining it and looking at its
execution plan.</p>

<p>A <code>COLLECT</code> is internally handled by an object called <code>AggregateNode</code>, so we have to look for that.
In the above screenshots, the <code>AggregateNode</code>s are tagged with either <strong>hash</strong> or <strong>sorted</strong>. This can
also be checked programatically by looking at the <code>aggregationOptions.method</code> attributes in the
JSON result of an explain().</p>

<p>Here is some example code to extract this information, limited to the <code>AggregateNode</code>s of the
query already:</p>

<p><code>js extracting just the AggregateNodes from an explain
var query = `
  FOR flight IN flights
  COLLECT from = flight._from WITH COUNT INTO count
  RETURN { from: from, count: count }
`;
var stmt = db._createStatement(query);
var plan = stmt.explain().plan;
plan.nodes.filter(function(node) {
  return node.type === 'AggregateNode';
});
</code></p>

<p>For the above query, this will produce something like this:</p>

<p>```json JSON explain result for AggregateNode
[
  {</p>

<pre><code>"type" : "AggregateNode", 
...
"aggregationOptions" : { 
  "method" : "hash" 
}  
</code></pre>

<p>  }
]
```</p>

<p>Here we can see that the query is using the <strong>hash</strong> method.</p>

<h2>Optimizing away post-COLLECT sorts</h2>

<p>If a query uses the <strong>hash</strong> method for a <code>COLLECT</code> but the sort order of the <code>COLLECT</code> result
is irrelevant to the user, the user can provide a hint to the optimizer to remove the
post-<code>COLLECT</code> sort.</p>

<p>This can be achieved by simplying appending a <code>SORT null</code> to the original <code>COLLECT</code> statement.
Here we can see that this removes the post-<code>COLLECT</code> sort:</p>

<p><img src="/downloads/screenshots/collect-nosort.png"></p>

<h2>Performance improvements</h2>

<p>The improvements achievable by using the <strong>hash</strong> method instead of the <strong>sorted</strong> method obviously
depend on whether there are appropriate indexes present for the group criteria. If an index can
be exploited, the <strong>sorted</strong> method may be just fine. However, there are cases when no indexes are
present, for example, when running arbitrary ad-hoc queries or when indexes are too expensive
(indexes need to be updated on insert/update/remove and also will use memory).</p>

<p>Following are a few comparisons of the <strong>sorted</strong> and the <strong>hash</strong> methods in case no indexes can be
used.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the setup for the test data. This generates 1M documents with both unique and repeating
string and numeric values. For the non-unique values, we&rsquo;ll use 20 different categories:</p>

<p>```js setting up test data
var test = db._create(&ldquo;test&rdquo;);
for (var i = 0; i &lt; 1000000; ++i) {
  test.insert({</p>

<pre><code>uniqueNumber: i, 
uniqueString: String("test" + i), 
repeatingNumber: (i % 20), 
repeatingString: String("test" + (i % 20)) 
</code></pre>

<p>  });
}
```</p>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s run the following query on the data and measure its execution time:</p>

<p><code>plain test query
FOR v IN test
  COLLECT value = v.@attribute WITH COUNT INTO count
  RETURN { value: value, count: count }
</code></p>

<p>The worst case is when the <code>COLLECT</code> will produce as many output rows as there are input
rows. This will happen when using a unique attribute as the grouping criterion. We&rsquo;ll run
tests on both numeric and string values.</p>

<p>Here are the execution times for unique inputs. It can be seen that the <strong>hash</strong> method
here will be beneficial if the post-<code>COLLECT</code> sort can be optimized away. As demonstrated
above, this can be achieved by adding an extra <code>SORT null</code> after the <code>COLLECT</code> statement.
If the post-<code>COLLECT</code> sort is not optimized away, it will make the hash method a bit more
expensive than the <strong>sorted</strong> method:</p>

<p>```plain COLLECT performance with unique inputs</p>

<h2>collect method       @attribute                duration</h2>

<p>sorted               uniqueNumber               11.92 s
hash                 uniqueNumber               13.40 s
hash (sort null)     uniqueNumber               10.13 s
sorted               uniqueString               22.04 s
hash                 uniqueString               27.35 s
hash (sort null)     uniqueString               12.12 s
```</p>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s check the results when we group on an attribute that is non-unique. Following
are the results for numeric and string attributes with 20 different categories each:</p>

<p>```plain COLLECT performance with non-unique inputs</p>

<h2>collect method       @attribute                duration</h2>

<p>sorted               repeatingNumber             5.56 s
hash                 repeatingNumber             0.94 s
hash (sort null)     repeatingNumber             0.94 s
sorted               repeatingString            10.56 s
hash                 repeatingString             1.09 s
hash (sort null)     repeatingString             1.09 s
```</p>

<p>In these cases, the result of the <code>COLLECT</code> will be much smaller than its input (we&rsquo;ll
only get 20 result rows out instead of 1M). Therefore the post-<code>COLLECT</code> sort for the <strong>hash</strong>
method will not make any difference, but the pre-<code>COLLECT</code> sort for the <strong>sorted</strong> method
will still need to sort 1M input values. This is also the reason why the <strong>hash</strong> method
is significantly faster here.</p>

<p>As usual, your mileage may vary, so please run your own tests.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Efficient Data Exports]]></title>
    <link href="http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/04/04/more-efficient-data-exports/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-04T21:51:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/04/04/more-efficient-data-exports</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently wrote about the <a href="https://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/04/01/improvements-for-the-cursor-api/">performance improvements for the cursor API</a>
made in ArangoDB 2.6. The performance improvements are due to a rewrite of the cursor API&rsquo;s internals.</p>

<p>As a byproduct of this rewrite, an extra API was created for exporting all documents from a
collection to a client application. With this being its only use case, it is clear that the new
API will not solve every data export problem. However, the API&rsquo;s limitedness facilitated a very efficient
implementation, resulting in <strong>nice speedups</strong> and <strong>lower memory usage</strong> when compared to the alternative
way of exporting all documents into a client application.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There did not exist an <em>official</em> export API before. So users often ran AQL queries like the following
to export all documents from a collection:</p>

<p><code>plain AQL query to export all documents
FOR doc IN collection
  RETURN doc
</code></p>

<p>While such AQL queries will work for smaller result sets, they will get problematic when results get
bigger. The reason is that the AQL very will effectively create a snapshot of all the documents present
in the collection. Creating the snapshot is required for data consistency. Once the snapshot is created,
clients can incrementally fetch the data from the snapshot and will still get a consistent result even
if the underlying collections get modified.</p>

<p>For smaller result sets, snapshotting is not a big issue. But when exporting all documents from a
bigger collection, big result sets will be produced. In this case, the snapshotting can become expensive
in terms of CPU time and also memory consumption.</p>

<p>We couldn&rsquo;t get around the snapshotting completely, but we could take advantage of the fact that when exporting
documents from a collection, all that can be snapshotted are documents. This is different to snapshotting
arbitrary AQL queries, which can produce any kind and combination of JSON.</p>

<p>Dealing only with documents allowed us to take an efficiency shortcut: instead of copying the complete
documents it will only copy pointers to the document revisions presently in th collection. Not only is this
much faster than doing a full copy of the document, but it also saves a lot of memory.</p>

<h2>Invoking the API</h2>

<p>While the invocation of the cursor API and the export API is slightly different, their result formats
have intentionally been kept similar. This way client programs do not need to be adjusted much to consume
the export API instead of the cursor API.</p>

<p>An example command for exporting via the cursor API is:</p>

<p>```bash exporting all documents via the cursor API
curl -X POST \</p>

<pre><code> "http://127.0.0.1:8529/_api/cursor" \
 --data '{"query":"FOR doc IN collection RETURN docs"}'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>A command for exporting via the new export API is:</p>

<p>```bash exporting all documents via the export API
curl -X POST \</p>

<pre><code> "http://127.0.0.1:8529/_api/export?collection=docs"
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>In both cases, the result will look like this:
```json API results
{
  &ldquo;result&rdquo;: [</p>

<pre><code>...
</code></pre>

<p>  ],
  &ldquo;hasMore&rdquo;:true,
  &ldquo;id&rdquo;:&ldquo;2221050516478&rdquo;
}
```</p>

<p>The <code>result</code> attribute will contain the first few (1,000 by default) documents. The
<code>hasMore</code> attribute will indicate whether there are more documents to fetch from the
server. In this case the client can use the cursor id specified in the <code>id</code> attribute
to fetch more result.</p>

<p>The API can be invoked via any HTTP-capable client such as <code>curl</code> (as shown above).</p>

<p>I have also added <a href="https://github.com/arangodb/arangodb-php/blob/devel/README.md#exporting_data">bindings to the ArangoDB-PHP driver</a>
today (contained in the driver&rsquo;s <code>devel</code> branch).</p>

<h2>API performance</h2>

<p>Now, what can be gained by using the export API?</p>

<p>The following table shows the execution times for fetching the first 1,000 documents
from collections of different sizes, both with via the cursor API and the export API.
Figures for the cursor API are shown for ArangoDB 2.5 and 2.6 (the version in which
it was rewritten):</p>

<p>```plain execution times for cursor API and export API</p>

<h1>of documents    cursor API (2.5)    cursor API (2.6)      export API</h1>

<hr />

<pre><code>   100,000               1.9 s               0.3 s          0.04 s
   500,000               9.5 s               1,4 s          0.08 s
 1,000,000              19.0 s               2.8 s          0.14 s
 2,000,000              39,0 s               7.5 s          0.19 s
 5,000,000               n/a                 n/a            0.55 s
10,000,000               n/a                 n/a            1.32 s
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Execution times are from my laptop, which only has 4 GB of RAM and a slow disk.</p>

<p>As can be seen, the rewritten cursor API in 2.6 is already much faster than the one
in 2.5. However, for exporting documents from one collection only, the new export API
is superior.</p>

<p>The export API also uses a lot less memory for snapshotting, as can be nicely seen in the
two bottom rows of the results. For these cases, the snapshots done by the cursor API
were bigger than the available RAM and the OS started swapping heavily. Snapshotting
didn&rsquo;t complete within 15 minutes, so no results are shown above.</p>

<p>Good news is that this didn&rsquo;t happen with the export API, due to the fact that the
snapshots it creates are much more compact.</p>

<p>Another nice side effect of the speedup is that the first results will arrive much
earlier in the client application. This will help in reducing client connection timeouts
in case clients are enforcing them on temporarily non-responding connections.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>ArangoDB 2.6 provides a specialized export API for exporting all documents from a
collection and shipping them to a client application. It is rather limited but
faster than the general-purpose AQL cursor API and can store its snapshots using less
memory.</p>

<p>Therefore, exporting all documents from bigger collections calls for using the new
export API from 2.6 on. The new export API is present in the <code>devel</code> branch, which
will eventually turn into a 2.6 release.</p>

<p>For other cases, when still using the cursor API, 2.6 will also provide significant
performance improvements when compared to 2.5. This can be seen from the comparison
table above and also from the observations made
<a href="https://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/04/01/improvements-for-the-cursor-api/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Improvements for the Cursor API]]></title>
    <link href="http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/04/01/improvements-for-the-cursor-api/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-01T13:59:22+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/04/01/improvements-for-the-cursor-api</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week we pushed some modifications for ArangoDB&rsquo;s cursor API into the <code>devel</code> branch.
The change will result in less copying of AQL query results between the AQL and the HTTP layers.
As a positive side effect, this will reduce the amount of garbage collection the built-in V8
has to do.</p>

<p>These modifications should improve the cursor API performance significantly for many cases,
while at the same time keeping its REST API stable.</p>

<p>This blog post shows some first unscientific performance tests comparing the old cursor API with
its new, improved implementation.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>A good way to test the cursor API performance is to issue lots of queries from the
ArangoShell. The ArangoShell will send the query to the server for execution. The server
will respond with the first 1,000 results for the query.</p>

<p>Additionally the server will create a server-side cursor if the result set is bigger than
1,000 documents. In this case, the ArangoShell will issue subsequent HTTP requests that fetch
the outstanding documents from the server.</p>

<p>The above behavior is triggered automatically when <code>db._query(query).toArray()</code> is run in
the ArangoShell.</p>

<p>Here is a test function that executes a query <em>n</em> times and measures the total execution time.
It will issue <em>n</em> HTTP requests to the server&rsquo;s cursor API for executing the query. It will
also issue further HTTP requests if the total result set size is bigger than 1,000 documents.
What is getting measured is thus the total execution time from the ArangoShell&rsquo;s point of view,
including time spent in the server-side cursor functions as well as in HTTP traffic.</p>

<p>```js function for testing the cursor API
var test = function(query, n) {
  var time = require(&ldquo;internal&rdquo;).time;
  var s = time();
  for (var i = 0; i &lt; n; ++i) {</p>

<pre><code>db._query(query).toArray(); 
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  return time() &ndash; s;
};
```</p>

<p>The test function was run with different queries to check which types of queries will benefit
from the cursor API change.</p>

<p>Note that the ArangoShell will issue all its requests to the cursor API sequentially. This is
ok for the purpose of this test, as the purpose was to measure the relative performance change
between the old and the new API implementation.</p>

<p>The ArangoShell and ArangoDB server were running on the same physical machine during the tests,
so this is a <strong>localhost</strong> benchmark.</p>

<h2>Detailed test results</h2>

<p>Here are the results from my local machine.</p>

<p>The first query was about the simplest one I could come up with. The query was sent to the
server 10,000 times. The result set size per query ws 1, resulting in 10,000 calls to the cursor
API with not much data to be transferred per call:</p>

<p><code>js test query
test("RETURN 1", 10000);
</code></p>

<p>Execution took 7.225 s with the old API, and 5.195 s with the new API (<strong>28 % improvement</strong>).</p>

<p>A query returning a slightly more complex result value:</p>

<p><code>js test query
test("RETURN { one: 'test', two: 'another-value', three: [ 1, 2, 3 ] }", 10000);
</code></p>

<p>This took 8.046 s with the old API, and 5.829 s with the new one (<strong>27 % improvement</strong>).</p>

<p>Another simple query, again executed 10,000 times, but now returning 10 values per query:</p>

<p><code>js test query
test("FOR i IN 1..10 RETURN i", 10000);
</code></p>

<p>Execution of this query took 7.951 s with the old, and 5.779 s with the new API (<strong>27 % improvement</strong>).</p>

<p>Now raising the number of return values per query from 10 to 1,000:</p>

<p><code>js test query
test("FOR i IN 1..1000 RETURN i", 10000);
</code></p>

<p>This took 31.650 s with the old, and 28.504 s with the new API (<strong>10 % improvement</strong>).</p>

<p>So far all query results contained 1,000 or less values. In this case the server is able to
send the whole query result in response in one go, so there were only as many calls to the
cursor API as there were queries. Even though the ArangoShell called the cursor API, the
cursor only existed temporarily on the server but directly vanished when the server sent its
response.</p>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s run a query that returns more than 1,000 values each. The first call to the
cursor API will then only return the first 1,000 results and additionally establish a
server-side cursor so the client can fetch more results. This will mean that for each client
query, there will be multiple HTTP requests.</p>

<p>The following run issues 100,000 calls to the cursor API (10,000 queries times 10 batches per
query):</p>

<p><code>js test query
test("FOR i IN 1..10000 RETURN i", 10000);
</code></p>

<p>This took 307.108 s with the old API, in contrast to 232.322 s with the new API (<strong>24 % improvement</strong>).</p>

<p>The next queries I tested were collection-based. They returned data from a collection named
<code>docs</code>. The collection contained 10,000 documents, and each document in the collection had
5 attributes.</p>

<p>The first query returned only a single one (random) document from the collection per query.</p>

<p><code>js test query
test("FOR i IN docs LIMIT 1 RETURN i", 10000);
</code></p>

<p>This took 8.689 s with the old API and 6.245 s with the new API (<strong>28 % improvement</strong>).</p>

<p>The next query returned all the documents from the collection. The query was executed
only 1,000 times because the result sets already got quite big. The combined size of all
result sets was 1,000,000 documents (10,000 documents, 1,000 queries).</p>

<p><code>js test query
test("FOR i IN docs RETURN i", 1000);
</code></p>

<p>This took 453.736 s with the old, and 197.543 s with the new API (<strong>56 % improvement</strong>).</p>

<p>The final query returned all document keys from the collection. The combined size of all result
sets was 10,000,000 values (10,000 documents, 10,000 queries):</p>

<p><code>js test query
test("FOR i IN docs RETURN i._key", 10000);
</code></p>

<p>With the old API, this took 529.765 s, and with the new API it took 348.243 s (<strong>34 % improvement</strong>).</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>The new cursor API was faster than its old counterpart for all queries tested here. Total execution
time as measured by the ArangoShell (representative for any other client program sending queries to
ArangoDB) was consistenly lower than it was with the old API implementation.</p>

<p>The improvements measured were varying. For the queries tested, the improvements fell into a range
of <strong>10 % to even more than 50 % speedup</strong>.</p>

<p>How much gain can be achieved in reality obviously depends on the type of query executed. There will
also be queries that do not benefit from the new API implementation. For example, queries that do not
return any results will not benefit much. This is because most of the optimizations done affect
the buffering and the data transport internals of the cursor API. Furthermore, queries that run for
a very long time but return only small amounts of data may not benefit considerably for the same reason.
However, there should not be any queries which are negatively affected by the change.</p>

<p>All in all, this looks quite promising, especially as the change will come <strong>for free</strong> for client
applications. Client programs do not need to be adjusted to reap the benefits. This is because all
that has changed were the <em>internals</em> of the cursor API. Its public REST interface remains unchanged.</p>

<p>The changes are included in the <code>devel</code> branch and can be tested there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AQL Improvements in 2.5]]></title>
    <link href="http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/02/26/aql-improvements-in-25/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-26T10:35:31+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/02/26/aql-improvements-in-25</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Contained in 2.5 are some small but useful AQL language improvements plus several AQL optimizer improvements.</p>

<p>We are working on further AQL improvements for 2.5, but work is still ongoing.
This post summarizes the improvements that are already completed and will be shipped with the initial ArangoDB
2.5 release.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h1>Language improvements</h1>

<h2>Dynamic attribute names</h2>

<p>Often the need arises to dynamically name object attributes in return values.
In AQL this was not directly possible so far, though there were some workarounds available to achieve about
the same result. <a href="https://docs.arangodb.com/cookbook/UsingDynamicAttributeNames.html">This recipe</a> summarizes
the options that are available to pre-ArangoDB 2.5 users.</p>

<p>With ArangoDB 2.5, dynamic attribute names can be constructed much more easily and flexibly. Object
attribute names in ArangoDB 2.5 can be specified using static string literals, bind parameters,
and dynamic expressions.</p>

<p>Dynamic expressions are most interesting, and to disambiguate them from other regular string literal attribute
names, dynamic attribute names need to be enclosed in square brackets (<code>[</code> and <code>]</code>). I have written about
that before in <a href="http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/02/03/using-dynamic-attribute-names-in-aql/">this blog</a>.</p>

<p>Here is an example query that uses the new syntax:</p>

<p><code>plain example query using dynamic attribute names
FOR i IN [ 17, 23, 42, 83 ]
  RETURN { [ CONCAT('value-of-', i, ' * ', i) ] : i * i }
</code></p>

<p>This will produce:</p>

<p>```json query result
[
  {</p>

<pre><code>"value-of-17 * 17" : 289 
</code></pre>

<p>  },
  {</p>

<pre><code>"value-of-23 * 23" : 529 
</code></pre>

<p>  },
  {</p>

<pre><code>"value-of-42 * 42" : 1764 
</code></pre>

<p>  },
  {</p>

<pre><code>"value-of-83 * 83" : 6889 
</code></pre>

<p>  }
]
```</p>

<h2>Functions added</h2>

<p>The following AQL functions have been added in 2.5:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>MD5(value)</code>: produces the MD5 hash of <code>value</code></li>
<li><code>SHA1(value)</code>: produces the SHA1 hash of <code>value</code></li>
<li><code>RANDOM_TOKEN(length)</code>: produces a pseudo-random string of the specified length.
 Such strings can be used for id or token generation. Tokens consist only of letters
 (lower and upper case) plus digits, so they are also URL-safe</li>
</ul>


<h1>Optimizer improvements</h1>

<h2>Optimizer rules</h2>

<p>The following AQL optimizer rules have been added in ArangoDB 2.5:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><code>propagate-constant-attributes</code></p>

<p>This rule will look inside <code>FILTER</code> conditions for constant value equality comparisons,
and insert the constant values in other places in <code>FILTER</code>s. For example, the rule will
insert <code>42</code> instead of <code>i.value</code> in the second <code>FILTER</code> of the following query:</p>

<pre><code>FOR i IN c1 
  FOR j IN c2 
    FILTER i.value == 42 
    FILTER j.value == i.value 
    RETURN 1
</code></pre></li>
<li><p><code>move-calculations-down</code></p>

<p>This rule moves calculations down in the execution plan as far as possible. The intention
is to move calculations beyond filters, in order to avoid calculations and computations
for documents that will be filtered away anyway.</p>

<p>If a query contains a lot of computations and a lot of documents will be skipped because
of filters, this rule might provide a big benefit.</p>

<p>A more detailed example is provided in
<a href="http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2015/01/31/yaor-yet-another-optimizer-rule/">this post</a>.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The already existing optimizer rule <code>use-index-for-sort</code> was also improved in the following way:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>the rule can now remove <code>SORT</code>s also in case a non-sorted index (i.e. a hash index) is used
for an equality lookup and all sort attributes are covered by the index.</p></li>
<li><p>the rule can also remove <code>SORT</code>s in case the sort critieria excludes the left-most index attributes,
but the left-most index attributes are used in a <code>FILTER</code> for equality-only lookups.</p>

<p>Here is an example that will use an existing skiplist index on [ <code>value1</code>, <code>value2</code> ] for sorting,
removing the extra <code>SORT</code>:</p>

<pre><code>FOR doc IN collection 
  FILTER doc.value1 == 1 
  SORT doc.value2 
  RETURN doc
</code></pre></li>
</ul>


<h2>Index usage</h2>

<p>The AQL optimizer now supports <a href="https://www.arangodb.com/2015/02/24/sparse-indexes-in-arangodb">sparse indexes</a>,
a feature added in 2.5.</p>

<p>It will use them automatically in queries when appropriate and when safe. Sparse indexes do exclude certain
documents purposely, so the optimizer always has to figure out whether it can use a sparse index to satisfy
a given <code>FILTER</code> condition.</p>

<p>The optimizer will also take into account index selectivity estimates when there are multiple index candidates.</p>

<h2>Estimates</h2>

<p>The optimizer estimates for the number of documents to be returned by a query or a subquery are more accurate
now for several types of queries. For example, if the optimizer can use a primary key, an edge index, or a hash
index in a given query part, it will use the index selectivity estimates for calculating the number of return
documents.</p>

<p>These estimates will be a lot more accurate than the previoulsy hard-coded filtering factors, and can lead to
better optimizer decisions and reporting (because estimates are returned in <code>explain</code> results, too).</p>

<h2>Memory savings</h2>

<p>Finally, the optimizer will now detect if the data-modification part in a data-modification query
can be executed in lockstep with the data-retrieval part of the same query. Previously, a data-modification
query always executed its data-retrieval part first, and then executed its data-modification part.
This could have resulted in big intermediate result sets which to retrieval part constructed in order
to pass them to the modification part of the query.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an example query:</p>

<p><code>plain data-modification query
FOR doc IN test
  INSERT doc INTO backup
</code></p>

<p>In the above query, the <code>FOR</code> loop is the retrieval part, and the <code>INSERT</code> is the modification part.
The optimizer in 2.5 will check if the two parts of the query are independent, and if it turns out they are,
will execute them in lockstep instead of sequentially.</p>

<p>The execution in lockstep is not necessarily faster than sequential execution, but it can save lots of
memory if the data-retrieval part constructed big intermediate result sets.</p>

<h1>Miscellaneous changes</h1>

<p>The AQL query execution statistics now also provide an attribute <code>filtered</code>. Its value indicates how many
documents were filtered by <code>FilterNode</code>s in the AQL query. This can be used as an indicator for whether
indexes should be added, and for how effective indexes are used for filtering.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Improved Non-unique Hash Indexes in 2.3]]></title>
    <link href="http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2014/11/07/improved-non-unique-hash-indexes/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-07T20:51:12+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jsteemann.github.io/blog/2014/11/07/improved-non-unique-hash-indexes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With ArangoDB 2.3 now getting into the <a href="https://www.arangodb.com/install-beta-version">beta stage</a>,
it&rsquo;s time to spread the word about new features and improvements.</p>

<p>Today&rsquo;s post will be about the changes made to non-unique hash
indexes.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Hash indexes allow looking up documents quickly if the indexed
attributes are all provided in a search query. They are not
suitable for range queries, but are the perfect choice if equality
comparisons are all that&rsquo;s needed.</p>

<p>Hash indexes have been available in ArangoDB ever since. There
have always been two variants of them:</p>

<ul>
<li>unique hash indexes</li>
<li>non-unique hash indexes</li>
</ul>


<p>There wasn&rsquo;t much to be done for unique hash indexes, and so there
haven&rsquo;t been any changes to them in 2.3. However, the non-unique
hash indexes were improved significantly in the new version.</p>

<p>The non-unique indexes already performed quite well if most of the
indexed values were unique and only few repetitions occurred. But their
performance suffered severly if the indexed attribute values repeated
a lot &ndash; that is, when the indexed value had a <strong>low cardinality</strong> and thus
the index had a <strong>low selectivity</strong>.</p>

<p>This was a problem because it slowed down inserting new documents into
a collection with such an index. And it also slowed down loading collections
with low cardinality hash indexes.</p>

<p>I am happy to state that in ArangoDB 2.3 this has been fixed, and the insert
performance of non-unique hash indexes has been improved significantly.
The index insertion time now scales quite well with the number
of indexed documents regardless of the cardinality of the indexed
attribute.</p>

<p>Following are a few measurements of non-unique hash index insertion
times from ArangoDB 2.3, for different cardinalities of the indexed
attribute.</p>

<p>The times reported are the net non-unique hash index
insertion times (the documents were present already, just the index
was created on them and index creation time was measured).</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start with a not too challenging case: indexing documents in
a collection with 100,000 different index values (<em>cardinality 100,000</em>):</p>

<p><code>text index insertion times for cardinality 100,000
number of documents:    128,000    =&gt;    time:   0.144 s
number of documents:    256,000    =&gt;    time:   0.231 s
number of documents:    512,000    =&gt;    time:   0.347 s
number of documents:  1,024,000    =&gt;    time:   0.694 s
number of documents:  2,048,000    =&gt;    time:   1.379 s
</code></p>

<p>The picture doesn&rsquo;t change much when reducing the cardinality
by a factor or 10 (i.e. <em>cardinality 10,000</em>):</p>

<p><code>text index insertion times for cardinality 10,000
number of documents:    128,000    =&gt;    time:   0.169 s
number of documents:    256,000    =&gt;    time:   0.194 s
number of documents:    512,000    =&gt;    time:   0.355 s
number of documents:  1,024,000    =&gt;    time:   0.668 s
number of documents:  2,048,000    =&gt;    time:   1.325 s
</code></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s again divide cardinality by 10 (now <em>cardinality 1,000</em>):</p>

<p><code>text index insertion times for cardinality 1,000
number of documents:    128,000    =&gt;    time:   0.130 s
number of documents:    256,000    =&gt;    time:   0.152 s
number of documents:    512,000    =&gt;    time:   0.261 s
number of documents:  1,024,000    =&gt;    time:   0.524 s
number of documents:  2,048,000    =&gt;    time:   0.934 s
</code></p>

<p><em>Cardinality 100</em>:</p>

<p><code>text index insertion times for cardinality 100
number of documents:    128,000    =&gt;    time:   0.114 s
number of documents:    256,000    =&gt;    time:   0.148 s
number of documents:    512,000    =&gt;    time:   0.337 s
number of documents:  1,024,000    =&gt;    time:   0.452 s
number of documents:  2,048,000    =&gt;    time:   0.907 s
</code></p>

<p><em>Cardinality 10</em>:</p>

<p><code>text index insertion times for cardinality 10
number of documents:    128,000    =&gt;    time:   0.130 s
number of documents:    256,000    =&gt;    time:   0.327 s
number of documents:    512,000    =&gt;    time:   0.239 s
number of documents:  1,024,000    =&gt;    time:   0.442 s
number of documents:  2,048,000    =&gt;    time:   0.827 s
</code></p>

<p>Finally we get to <em>cardinality 1</em>, the definitive indicator
for the index being absolutely useless. Let&rsquo;s create it anyway,
for the sake of completeness of this post:</p>

<p><code>text index insertion times for cardinality 1
number of documents:    128,000    =&gt;    time:   0.130 s
number of documents:    128,000    =&gt;    time:   0.095 s
number of documents:    256,000    =&gt;    time:   0.146 s
number of documents:    512,000    =&gt;    time:   0.246 s
number of documents:  1,024,000    =&gt;    time:   0.445 s
number of documents:  2,048,000    =&gt;    time:   0.925 s
</code></p>

<p>On a side note: all indexed values were numeric. In absolute terms,
indexing string values will be slower than indexing numbers, but insertion
should still scale nicely with the number of documents as long as everything
fits in RAM.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
